There's always a contrast on how to
start these kinds of videos.
I could be like totally extreme, acting
all hyper excitable, trying to convince
you how incredibly excited I am. Or
could opt for like a Mr. Rogers or Bob
Ross vibe.
Hey there, friend. What a wonderful day
it is to talk a bit about fiber.
At any rate, I want you to know two
things from the outset. One, fiber has
consistently been linked to improvements
in health across many studies in humans.
And two, one of the main mechanisms
attributed to fiber's mass health
improvement effect is due to its ability
to be taken up by microbes in your
intestines and for it to be turned into
what is known as short-chain fats. These
short-chain fats improve our health
through a number of ways as they
interact with our different organs.
Now, what I just told you is true, but
it's
boring.
And I wouldn't have been able to say
that just a few months ago, but because
this study released, I have that luxury.
You'll soon understand why.
Essentially, the researchers made mice
unhealthy by feeding them fructose, a
type of sugar that has been implicated
many times over as being harmful to
health. Now, for example, it leads your
liver to produce more fat, which
contributes to fatty liver disease. But
along with the mice that were fed
fructose, there was another group fed
fructose plus a fiber called inulin. And
when looking at their livers compared,
we see some striking differences. The
more white that you see, the more fat
has disturbed the integrity of the liver
tissue. Now, I'm sure you noticed the CF
condition there. That's the fructose
only condition. Yeah. Not looking too
pretty, is it? The condition next to it,
IF there, is the fructose plus inulin,
the fiber. If we just focus on those
two, it's clear that fiber leads to
substantial reductions in liver fat. So,
the takeaway here is in the big picture,
fiber improves our health, but in a more
specific sense, fiber protects our liver
from the fructose-caused liver
fattiness. But while that's interesting
in and in line with considerable human
research, it's not why I'm excited about
this study.
What's got my attention is the multiple
ways that fiber enacts these effects.
For example, the researchers discovered
that inulin, again, that's the fiber,
reduces the accumulation of fat in the
liver by reducing the expression or the
production of lipogenesis genes. In
plain English, it reduces the production
of proteins or enzymes responsible for
converting fructose into fat
that then burdens the liver cells.
Beyond that, it encourages the liver
cells to metabolize or break down fat
molecules. But even beyond that,
something else was discovered, something
called the fructose spillover effect.
One of the issues with fructose
consumption is that it spills over from
the intestines to the liver, where it
causes the harm that we discussed. So,
excess fattiness is just one example.
Although, it also contributes to
fibrosis, so the worsening of the liver
integrity. Anyway,
it can also spill over into the colon,
the later section of the intestine, and
cause dysbiosis, an accumulation of
unwanted microbes, as well as generate
excess fats that are then transported to
the liver and further burden it with a
nutrient that it's already overwhelmed
in. Fascinatingly, when we look at the
amount of fructose in the intestinal
tract, the first two are the part of the
initial sections of the intestine, so
the small intestine, and the last one is
the colon, where we don't want fructose.
Otherwise, we get this spillover effect.
It doesn't take a rocket scientist to
figure out that the IF and CIF
conditions there, which are both fiber
supplemented, show no fructose in the
colon, thereby proving that the
spillover effect is nullified with
fiber. So, far more interesting than
just fiber produces short-chain fats
that help our body. We now know multiple
new mechanisms by which fiber helps us,
and it in this context, especially
against fructose.
One, it reduces the generation of fat in
the liver. Two, it increases the
metabolism of fat molecules. And three,
it protects the colon from experiencing
fructose spillover. In fact, it goes on
because fiber also changes our
metabolism to begin generating out of
bad bad fructose a new series of
proteins that have wide-reaching
benefits within our body. In fact,
you may even be supplementing to try to
raise these proteins. And it has some
other potent effects that I'll get into
like why fructose disappears from the
colon or some additional effects on the
liver and more. But alas, it is too much
for me to fit into this video. So, I'm
going to be including it in my much
extended, more detailed version,
exclusive for the Physionic Insiders,
along with an extensive article
detailing everything for you, along with
more specifics on how to take advantage
of all this information for ourselves.
Anyway, if you're interested, plus all
these perks right here, consider joining
the Insiders. The link is in the
description.
Okay. Now,
we know all this comes down to the fiber
inulin, but where do we get inulin?
Here's a non-exhaustive list of foods
that contain a sizeable amount of
inulin.
Or, of course, there's always ways of
supplementation, but some people get
gastrointestinal discomfort from
concentrated amounts, so consider
spreading it out when possible if that's
you. All this to say that inulin, a
dietary fiber, improves liver health
through a number of mechanisms, all
revolving around protecting the liver
from becoming a fatty liver, or
scientifically called a steatotic liver,
which can grow into inflammation and
fibrosis. So, prioritize inulin sources,
especially if you have non-alcoholic
liver disease, like varieties of roots,
garlics, leeks, and so on. Oh, and I
realize that you could just avoid
fructose, but some of these benefits are
independent of fructose, so you'd also
be missing out on some of the other
benefits. Although, avoiding sugary
drinks filled with fructose ain't such a
bad idea. We agree there, too. And hey
friend, won't you join me in another
video on the relationship between fiber
and cancer? That sounds like it'd be a
fun time, DOESN'T IT? GUYS, IT'S
MIND-BLOWING FUN. JUST click on the
video.
Thanks for tuning in. Speak soon.